[ gentle upbeat music ]
- Man is omnipotent .
Nothing is impossible for him .
What seemed to be unthinkable undertakings yesterday
are history today .
The conquest of the moon , for example .
Who talks about it anymore ?
Today , we are already on
the threshold of conquering our galaxy
and in a not too distant tomorrow ,
we 'll be considering the conquest of the universe .
And yet , man seems to ignore the fact
that on this very planet ,
there are still people living in the stone age
and practicing cannibalism .
Primitive tribes isolated
in a ruthless , hostile environment
where the prevailing law is the survival of the fittest .
And this jungle , which its inhabitants refer to
as the Green Inferno is only a few hours flying time
from New York City .
Was it to remind us of this ,
that four brave young Americans
went there to make a documentary on life in the jungle ?
Was it also to remind us ,
for instance , that before venturing into space
we should become more acquainted
with the planet we live on ?
Four young and fearless Americans ,
children of the space age ,
armed with cameras , microphones and curiosity .
Alan Yates , the director ,
famous for his documentaries on Vietnam and Africa .
Faye Daniels , his girlfriend and script girl ,
and their two cameramen and inseparable friends ,
Jack Anders and Mark Tomaso .
Four youngsters who never came back .
But let 's have a look at them
at the beginning of their incredible adventure .
Here at the border between Brazil and Peru ,
they are about to board a plane
that will take them to the Rio Ocoro ,
a last outpost from which they will continue on foot
deep into the Amazon Jungle
into the area known as the Green Inferno .
- Hey , are you really not scared ?
- Not at all .
I 've been in plenty other dangerous places with him .
- [ Interviewer ] What about you , Alan ?
- Well , there 's only one thing that scares me
and that 's marriage .
[ everyone laughs ]
- He 'd take me to the North Pole to put it off .
[ Alan groans ]
- [ Interviewer ] I 'd say he succeeded this time , too .
- And this is the last time .
- Yeah , provided we come back in one piece .
All right , all right .
Let 's go .
- Well , you four certainly aren 't the first
to embark on such an adventure .
There was an expedition in ' 59 and another in ' 67
and neither of them came back .
- Ah , yeah , that was Smith and that bunch of Frenchmen .
- Yes .
- Yeah , Frenchmen .
They were amateurs , a bunch of jerks .
They never succeeded in doing anything .
- For us , the difficult doesn 't exist
and the impossible takes just a little more time .
- We 'll be back .
- [ Faye ] We 'll be back .
- We have Felipe our guide .
Say hi to the camera . [ everyone cheers ]
[ plane propeller whirs ]
[ plane engine roars ]
- [ Reporter ] Those are the last pictures we have of them .
Two months have passed since they were last heard from .
Are they still alive and , if so , where are they ?
These are the questions that the rescue team
sponsored by New York University
and the Pan American Broadcasting System
hope to be able to answer .
[ upbeat music ]
- [ Faculty Member ] Thank you for accepting ,
Professor Monroe .
Good luck .
- [ Reporter ] Professor Harold Monroe ,
NYU 's noted anthropologist ,
has taken part in various expeditions
exploring primitive cultures ,
but this will be his first journey into Amazonia .
[ anxious music ]
[ birds squawking ]
[ birds chirping ] [ anxious music ]
[ intense ominous music ]
[ guns firing ]
[ dart whizzes ] [ soldier groans ]
[ gun firing ]
- Help him .
[ gun fire cracking ]
[ guns firing ]
[ birds chirping ]
[ footsteps crunching ]
[ gun firing ]
[ soldier moans ]
[ speaking foreign language ] Hold it !
Look at this ... a cannibal with a lighter !
[ birds calling ] [ insects trilling ]
Poor Oliveira
only 20 years old ...
Once it hits the bloodstream , there 's nothing you can do ...
Better a bullet than a dart dipped with curare .
But we gave him the serum right away !
Sure , the serum ...
It only works half the time
if it isn 't already too old by the time we get it .
They 'd just love to blow his head off because of Oliveira .
So would I !
But that American is coming
and we 've got orders to help him .
He 's lucky ...
A Yacumo prisoner is like a passport into the Green Inferno .
[ plane engine roaring ]
[ water splashes ] [ plane engine roaring ]
[ upbeat radio music ]
- Here you are , Lieutenant .
- Well , Professor Monroe .
- Do you think you could turn that ?
Thanks .
- All I can say is that you anthropologists
and missionaries are made out of special stuff .
If hell holes like this didn 't exist ,
I 'm sure you would invent them .
Whereas I would give both my ,
well , let 's say I 'd give anything to be somewhere else .
- Look , Lieutenant . I 'll be as little trouble as possible .
It 's just , I 'm sure you 've got
enough problems of your own . [ insect buzzing ]
But I 'll have to be , to be honest with you .
No , no-no , thanks .
I need your help in , in organizing this expedition .
- How can I refuse ?
You have been recommended by everybody in our government ,
as well as yours .
Only , I sure can 't guarantee
that you 'll still be breathing when you return .
- Look , I know this is not going to be a picnic .
Believe me , this is not my first trip into the bush .
[ Lieutenant spits ]
- A skunk must have pissed in that .
[ birds chirping ]
- Lieutenant , this lighter belonged to Faye Daniels .
- Come with me , Professor .
I 'll introduce you to your guide .
He 's the best there is , if you can get along with him .
It 's full of shit . Clean it !
- [ Lieutenant ] Hey , Chaco , this is Professor Monroe .
- Hello ?
It 's nice to meet you .
The Lieutenant here was telling me what a ,
what an excellent guide you are .
- You 're gonna take all this with you in the jungle ?
- [ Harold ] Yes .
- Well , forget it .
We 're gonna need some weapons ,
some ammunition , plus some medicine .
That 's all we need .
I already told your friends .
In there , the more you carry ,
the quicker you get tired , the sooner you die .
- All right . All right .
All I wanna know Mr. Chaco is ,
do we have a chance of finding them alive ?
- Who 's to say ?
The only thing I know is , we 're gonna risk our lives
to save those fuckers .
Let 's go see the Yacumos .
[ Harold scoffs ]
Great warriors , these Yacumos .
They 're afraid of no one , except for the Tree People .
- Tree People ?
- No White man has ever seen them
or the ones who have never lived to tell about it .
[ Chaco speaking in foreign language ]
- Did you see this ?
Looks like the sacred scar of Ateri .
- That 's what it is .
He 's the son of a shaman
and he 's been consecrated to the spirit of the jaguar ,
which also explains what they were doing this far from home .
- What do you mean ?
- Ah , they were caught ,
yet , they 're not really cannibals .
Which means it was probably some religious ceremony
meant to chase evil spirits outta the jungle ,
White men 's spirits .
[ monkey chattering ]
[ ominous music ]
[ ominous music ] [ birds calling ]
Quit worrying about the Yacumos .
You can 't afford to waste your strength helping that savage .
He 'll outlive all of us .
[ creatures screeching ] [ birds calling ]
[ ominous music ]
[ Harold pants ] Can you make it ?
[ birds screeching ]
We 'll have to wade across .
But there 's no piranhas here .
Come on .
[ creatures screeching ]
Come on , come on !
There may not be any piranhas ,
but there 's always a few hungry caiman around .
[ monkeys screeching ]
[ Miguel yelling ]
[ Chaco laughs ]
Leeches .
[ monkey screeches ]
[ birds warbling ]
Leave that shit alone .
- Well , he can 't do it by himself
and there 's three of us here , why can 't we help ?
- Don 't try it again , Professor .
Here we do as I say
and this bastard has to know who 's the strongest .
[ Chaco speaking in foreign language ]
- Oh , that 's terrific .
- Chaco 's right , SeÃ ± or .
This guy is all hate .
As soon as you don 't look , he 'll slit your throat .
[ birds chirping ]
[ twigs clatter ]
- They passed this way .
Yacumos dig a hole to cook .
- That means we are following the same trail , right ?
- [ Chaco ] Right .
- We 're very lucky .
[ monkeys screeching ]
[ leopard growls ]
[ birds chirping ]
[ gun firing ]
[ insects trilling ] [ bird warbling ]
[ dramatic music ]
[ creatures trilling ]
[ Harold retches ]
- Hey , Professor , I recognize these teeth .
This is Felipe Ocana .
He knew the jungle as well as I do .
- That makes me feel terrific .
- I wonder what was his mistake ?
[ Harold groans ]
See that , we 're near his village .
He can already smell his home .
- Hey , hey !
Amiga .
[ Chaco laughs ]
- Here comes dinner .
- Hey , amiga . A muskrat .
Today , we eat meat , okay ?
- That 's Miguel .
Hurry up , I 'm hungry .
- [ Miguel ] Yeah . Huh !
[ muskrat screeches ]
- Some diet , that 's for sure .
Hey Chaco , what the hell are you doing ?
- It 's for our Yacumo friend .
With a little bit of this stuff in him ,
he will forget all about trying to run away tonight .
[ Chaco speaking in foreign language ]
[ birds chirping ]
[ Yacumo snorts ]
Yeah , this will make him very happy .
Just wait and see .
- Drug addicts in the jungle .
[ Chaco shorts ]
[ Chaco laughs ]
- Hey , give him some of this , a little muskrat stomach .
He 'll love it .
- You like it , huh ?
Right , eat . It 's all yours .
Go on stuff yourself .
[ ominous music ]
[ bound person moaning ]
[ troubling music ]
[ dramatic music ]
- What the hell is that ?
You know , I swear ,
that looks like a ritualistic punishment for adultery .
- [ Chaco ] That 's what it is .
Just sit back and enjoy the show ,
' cause afterwards he 's going to take us to the village .
[ adulteress moans ] [ sombre music ]
[ adulteress screaming ]
[ adulteress sobbing ]
[ sombre music ]
[ adulteress screams ]
[ adulteress sobbing ]
[ adulteress screaming ] [ dramatic music ]
Don 't be a fool !
Come on , Professor .
[ dramatic music ]
[ adulteress screams ] [ dramatic music ]
[ rock thuds ]
[ sombre music ]
[ water ripples ]
That punishment is considered a divine commandment .
If he had not killed her , the tribe would 've killed him .
Here he comes .
[ Yacumo sobbing ] [ birds chirping ]
[ gun firing ]
[ Yacumo indistinctly chattering ]
Follow him .
[ creatures chattering ]
Well it is no masterpiece , but it 'll do .
Can you guess what it 's for , Professor ?
- Oh , let me try , Chaco .
Please , let me try .
Okay , is it possible that this way
they won 't know how many of us there are
until we can talk with them , huh ?
- He 's learning fast , huh , Miguel ?
- Like lightning .
- Oh , terrific . Just terrific .
[ birds warbling ]
[ grass rustling ]
- [ Chaco ] They 're coming .
- [ Harold ] Where ? I don 't see a thing .
- Don 't worry . They 're there .
- I know they 're there .
I know they 're there , but where ? I don 't see anything .
- Come on . Let 's send out our ambassador .
Andale , Miguel .
- Super kid .
- [ speaks in foreign language ] , Miguel .
[ Miguel speaking in foreign language ]
Andale , muchacho .
[ birds chirping ]
[ insects trilling ]
[ rhythmic drums beating ]
We may be in trouble .
- God , you 've raised deductive reasoning to an art .
- Instinct , something says your friends
made quite a mess of things .
[ rhythmic drums beating ]
[ darts whizzing ]
Wait !
If Miguel pulls this off ,
I swear I 'll buy him a bottle of whiskey .
[ darts whizzing ]
[ rhythmic drums beating ]
This is supposed to demonstrate their good intentions .
[ stick splashes ]
[ birds chirping ]
There , they 're gonna show themselves now .
[ Yacumo chattering ]
[ Miguel shouting in foreign language ]
[ Miguel speaking in foreign language ]
- Where the hell are you going ?
They 're gonna lead you right into an ambush .
- No , this is a good sign , Professor .
- Oh , yeah ? You coulda have fooled me .
- Ah , they just want to show us they are brave warriors
and they want us to follow them to their village .
- Follow them ?
- Yeah , to return the prisoner and to talk .
- Hey listen , I-I don 't know about this .
I think they want us for dinner tonight .
- Help me now .
[ birds warbling ]
[ parrots screeching ]
[ creatures screeching ]
[ rhythmic drums beating ]
[ Yacumo women chattering ]
[ Yacumo speaking in foreign language ]
[ rhythmic drums beating ]
[ dramatic music ]
Pretend you 've seen nothing .
- Okay .
[ ominous music ]
[ creatures chattering ]
[ Yacumo yelling ]
[ sombre music ]
[ Yacumo wails ]
- Your friends shot him .
Let 's hope he doesn 't die before we pull out .
Get busy , Miguel !
[ Miguel speaking in foreign language ]
[ blade clicks ]
[ tribe murmuring ]
[ Yacumo wails ]
[ blade clicks ]
[ Miguel speaking in foreign language ]
[ blade clicks ] [ tribe cheers ]
You can breathe easy .
It 's all right now , Professor .
[ rhythmic drums beating ]
[ Yacumo chanting in foreign language ]
[ Chaco speaking in foreign language ]
Cheers , Professor .
You now have the rare honor of drinking hisimo .
[ Yacumo chanting in foreign language ]
- Yay .
[ birds warbling ] [ water splashing ]
[ Yacumos chattering ]
[ group chattering ]
[ birds warbling ]
[ thunder booming ]
The group we are looking for
was probably headed toward the centre of the jungle
or the centre of the mato ,
which no White man has ever seen before .
This area is under the domination of two cannibal tribes .
They are so fierce ,
they 're feared by all of the tribes in the area ,
including the tough courageous warriors
of the Yacumo tribe .
These two superpowers of the Green Inferno
are perpetually at war with each other ;
the Yamamomo or Tree People
and the Shamatari , the Swamp People .
Each considers the other fair game .
Hunted and then eaten .
[ rain pelting ] [ thunder booming ]
[ tape recorder whirs ]
- This will keep you high and dry .
- No thanks .
The Yacumo blame Alan Yate 's group
for the great calamity that befell them .
Exactly what happened remains a mystery .
We only know the four Whites -
- Hey ! Shut that off !
- [ Harold ] Then moved on .
- God , we 're in the middle of a hunt !
- Tree People or both ?
- Hunting each other .
Let 's get going .
[ ominous music ]
[ birds chirping ]
[ tribe members chattering ]
Up there , the Shamatari are trying to flush their prey .
[ ominous music ]
[ Shamatari chattering ]
[ person coughing ]
[ branches rustling ]
[ flames crackling ]
[ people coughing ]
[ ominous music ]
[ person sobbing ]
[ person screams ]
[ body thuds ]
[ Shamatari chattering ]
[ blows thudding ]
[ anxious music ]
[ Shamatari chattering ]
[ victims yelling ]
[ anxious music ]
[ Shamatari grunting ] [ victim yelling ]
[ Shamatari chattering ]
[ dramatic music ]
[ both tribes shouting ]
[ gun fires ]
[ person moans ]
[ dramatic music ]
[ guns firing ]
- [ Harold ] Despite the fact that our intervention
saved them from the Shamatarri ,
the Tree People although they 've welcomed us
into their territory ,
continue to behave strangely towards us
with a mixture of fear and distrust .
[ tape recorder clicks ]
Nevertheless , we 've been permitted
to observe the execution of one of their warriors ,
death by mutilation .
The criminal thwarts the chief .
[ chief chants ]
[ tape recorder clicks ]
The criminal , from the way he was destroyed ,
must 've done something horrible
to incur the wrath of his own people .
It is not clear whether this was
to pay a debt of honor toward us
or only to demonstrate how to dispense justice .
- [ Chaco ] Careful , referring to us .
[ chief chants ]
[ tribe chants ]
- We weren 't able to get anything out of the Yanomamo ,
except for the wristwatch they gave us
as a token of the gratitude to an ally ,
An ally they continued to fear and mistrust .
So I decided to try an experiment in psychology ,
to strip myself completely ;
clothes , weapons , dog tags , rings , everything
to become like them , naked and unfettered as Adam .
[ water splashing ]
[ upbeat music ]
[ Yacumos laughing ]
[ group laughing ] [ group chattering ]
[ upbeat music ]
[ Yacumos chattering ]
[ Yacumos wailing ]
[ dramatic music ]
The Tree People would not let us bury the ghastly remains
they had painted ochre to drive away the evil spirits
which the dead represented .
Once again , I asked myself what unspeakable crime
could 've called for such atrocious retribution ?
I know our lives are hanging by a thread ,
but I can turn back without , at least ,
trying to recover the footage that Alan Yates
and the others paid for with their lives .
I am thinking of the enormous human
and scientific interest it 's going to contain .
I must do something .
Chaco and Miguel can 't possibly understand this .
Yet , I must somehow gain the confidence of these savages .
After all , they too have rules of conduct .
[ birds chirping ]
- [ Miguel ] Hold it !
[ Miguel grunts ]
[ birds chirping ]
[ gun firing ]
[ gun clatters ]
[ chief chanting on recorder ]
[ tribe chattering ]
[ bird cawing ]
[ tribe chanting ]
[ chief speaking in foreign language ]
[ tape recorder clicks ]
[ tribe chanting ]
- You did it , god damn it .
You just invited us to dinner .
[ tribe chanting ]
- I what ?
[ tribe chanting ] [ chief chanting ]
[ recorder chief chanting ]
[ flesh crunches ]
[ chief on recorder chanting ] [ people chanting ]
[ bird screeching ]
By some incredible act of God ,
they hadn 't tried to open them .
We 're hoping the climate didn 't damage them too much .
- And so in exchange for the tape recorder ,
the cannibal chief let you take away the cans of film .
Is that it ?
- Yes , they thought that since I was capable
of capturing the human voice ,
I was also capable of capturing their spirit .
This convinced them
that I was the only one capable of breaking the evil spell
that had been cast over the tribe
by their murder of the Whites .
Of course , they had no inkling
of what was really in those cans .
How could you explain what a movie is ?
They just felt that they were a threat .
- Why do you say threat ?
- Well , the Yamamomos understood
how important these film cans were to Alan Yates
and his crew .
They thought the silver boxes contained their power .
The power which I must say ,
again , caused much damage and violence .
- Fantastic story .
Thank you , Professor Monroe .
- You 're very welcome .
- As we conclude this special interview ,
we would like to remind you that Wednesday
at 9 : 00 PM here on Pantheon ,
we 'll be presenting Part One of " The Green Inferno " ,
the dramatic film testimony of an extraordinary adventure
that took its protagonists
all the way back to the stone age .
- And you would be the ideal host for the program .
- That 's right .
Professor Monroe , as an eyewitness as well as a scientist ,
you would be the most -
- Yes , but before I make any decision on this ,
I 'd like to review all the film materials .
As of yet , we 've seen none of it .
- Professor Monroe ,
I can assure you that they knew exactly what they wanted .
- That may be .
But meanwhile , they 're all dead aren 't they ?
- Which is exactly why
we have to let the public know the truth .
We 'll let the people be the judge .
Better yet , we 'll let the people
who knew them best be the judge ;
their parents , their wives .
This is a documentary they shot for us
about a year and a half ago .
- [ Bill ] Can I start ?
- [ Harold ] Yes , please do .
[ guns firing ]
- [ Person ] Stop ! Stop !
[ guns firing ] [ people chattering ]
[ solemn music ]
[ person shouting in foreign language ]
[ officer speaking in foreign language ]
[ solemn music ]
[ guns firing ]
[ bells tinkling ]
[ solemn music ]
[ gun fires ]
[ person shouts ] [ guns firing ]
[ film clicks ]
- Pretty powerful stuff , huh ?
Well , just to give you an idea
how Alan and the others worked ,
everything you just saw was a put on .
- You mean this wasn 't -
- That was no enemy army approaching .
Alan paid those soldiers to do a bit of acting for him .
You 'll have to excuse me now , I 'll join you later .
- [ Harold ] Yes , thank you .
- Shall I go ahead ?
- Yeah , why not ?
[ gentle music ]
- [ Bill ] This is Jack .
Faye ... Alan ...
and this is Mark .
They 'd worked together for years .
They were terrible prima-donnas , of course ,
but I have to admit they were real pros .
- [ Harold ] Um-hm .
- [ Bill ] The stuff they shot could really gut punch ya .
- [ Harold ] Yeah , I can imagine .
- [ Bill ] Their ratings were fantastic , you know .
Higher than most of the big comics .
and did they know how to play an audience ,
Alan especially .
Look at this bit they shot before leaving .
- Yeah , we 're coming back anyway .
We got , Felipe , our guide . Come on , come on up here .
Yay !
[ group laughing ]
Damn it . Yeah , there we go .
Okay , ah-huh !
[ plane engine humming ]
- [ Bill ] This shot 's dark ,
because the diaphragm setting on the camera was wrong .
There , now he 's got it right .
- Forget it .
There 's no electricity where we 're going .
Nope , this is anything
but a well organized safari with all the comforts .
Weapons , camera , medicinal supplies .
That 's about it .
Since , we 'll be covering hundreds of miles on foot .
And that 's another thing ,
who knows when we 'll have another shower .
Of course , I don 't think Faye 'll have any problem
remaining the sexiest script girl in history .
- Are you really shooting ? Jerk !
- Okay . Okay , that 's enough .
- Has anyone seen my pants anywhere ?
- [ Mark ] What do you want those for ?
- To put them on my head , stupid !
- [ Alan ] I thought ever since Jack
took them off two years ago ,
you didn 't need them anymore .
Right , Mark ?
- [ Mark ] Right , nice [ speaking faintly ] .
- Knock it off .
Are you shooting again ?
[ Jack chuckles ]
Idiot !
- Crew of clowns .
- They had a great sense of the theatrical .
- Like I said , real professionals .
- What was I saying , Professor ?
Yeah , I tried working with Alan a couple of times
and I just couldn 't handle it .
You know he , he pushed his people to the limit
demanding everything , including blood .
And talk about paranoia .
God have mercy on his soul ,
he was one ruthless son of a bitch !
- So I feel we have a duty
to tell the public their story , Mr. Yates .
- [ sighs ] Alan , I don 't know .
[ gentle music ]
You know I really appreciate your coming .
You 're the first person to come
and talk to me about Alan after what happened .
What I 'd like to know , Professor ,
is what did happen to my son ?
Can you tell me ?
[ gentle flute music ]
- Faye ? No , that wasn 't her real name .
She always wanted to be an actress .
Her real name was Tina .
Excuse me a minute .
Children , look , I 'm just going to be
speaking with this man one more minute
and then we 'll play , okay ?
As you can tell , we 're very different in our characters .
But Tina was very energetic , very hard working .
Very ambitious , extremely ambitious .
I used to say to her ,
do you think that you 'll ever be at peace with yourself ?
Anyway , now she is .
God rest her soul .
- [ Mrs. Anders ] Elizabeth ! Elizabeth !
- [ Harold ] Excuse me , Mrs. Anders .
Just two minutes .
How did you feel about Jack ?
- What 's the use ?
What am I supposed to say about Jack ?
After two years of marriage ,
I was with him for just four months .
- Hi .
- I 'll see ya , huh .
- [ Woman On Bike ] Bye-bye .
- He was always on assignments ;
India , Asia , Africa .
Yeah , sure , he was good in bed , but he liked to eat too .
No brains , though .
He 's too easily influenced .
[ scoffs ] Alan was his God , you know ?
You know what I mean ?
Hey , you guys think I could get any bread out of this ?
- [ Harold ] Uh , Mr. Tomaso .
Mr. Tomaso , please .
I just wanna ask you one question
about your son . - Yeah ,
what do you wanna ask me ?
- [ Harold ] Look , your son was a man of special importance
to the news world .
Can you tell me something about him ?
- My son ? My son is no good .
He doesn 't work . He doesn 't go to school .
Wants to lay around the house all day
and he 's no good , period .
Now , that 's it . I gotta go back to my job .
Don 't bother me no more .
- [ Harold ] But about Mr. Tomaso , please .
Your son was
well known to a lot of people . - I already told you .
- [ Harold ] Just one question .
Just one . - Okay , one question .
- [ Harold ] About your son ,
I-I just wanna know what kind of man was he ?
- My son ? My son was a son of a bitch and he was no good .
That 's it . My son is dead .
I don 't wanna talk about him no more .
Now leave you alone . Goodbye .
- [ Harold ] Mr. Tomaso , millions of Americans .
Mr. Tomaso , please !
[ siren pulsing ]
- Why didn 't they print the whole thing ?
- The negative needed special treatment ,
because of the humidity .
The quality isn 't the best ,
but it 's pretty good considering the lousy conditions
they were shooting in .
- Unfortunately , two reels were light fogged
and we had to throw them out .
- I put a piece of black leader
between one sequence and another .
- Good , that 's where we 'll put the interviews
with the families
and the one in which you talk about your search for them .
Go ahead , Bill .
- Okay .
[ film reel clicking ]
- [ Bill ] This first segment is silent .
Evidently , they didn 't always use their mics ,
though , they were attached right to the camera .
Just above the lens , like a gun barrel . See ?
[ film reel clicking ]
Remember this is a very rough cut ,
almost like watching rushes .
A lot of the stuff will be thrown out during the actual editing .
Here we are . Should be some sound coming in now .
No-no , not yet . Here .
[ Felipe laughing ]
Felipe .
[ bird squawking ]
- [ Jack ] Okay , speak now .
- We 've been walking for six days
in this marvelous inferno .
Today is Saturday the 25th .
If I were in New York right now ,
I 'd probably be out shopping .
[ water splashing ]
[ Jack yells ]
- [ Alan ] Get the camera !
Damn thing !
- Wait , wait , wait !
Look out [ speaking faintly ] .
[ mic squeals ]
[ dramatic music ]
[ knife scraping ]
[ Faye retches ]
[ dramatic music ]
[ hatchet thudding ]
[ sombre music ]
[ film reel clicking ]
[ birds chirping ]
- How much of the material is without sound ?
- Less than half .
- Ah .
- [ Bill ] Every so often ,
I 've laid in some stock music
to juice things up a little .
[ birds squawking ]
- [ Alan ] What is it ?
- [ Felipe ] The Yacumos passed this way .
We 're not far from the village .
- [ Alan ] All right .
[ Faye screaming ]
- [ Jack ] Pull it off !
- Not yet , wait !
Jack , the camera . Get the camera !
No , not yet ! Wait !
Move away ! Jack , get this shot !
[ Faye moaning ]
- This is fucking dangerous ! You know !
This is fucking
[ Faye ] Shut the fuck up !
[ Faye panting ]
- Okay , okay . You 're all right .
[ Faye screaming ]
Ah !
[ stick thudding ]
[ Faye sobbing ]
[ Alan laughing ]
- [ Jack ] Look here !
- [ Alan ] We 've been walking through the jungle for days
with the harrowing feeling that we 're moving in circles .
At night we have to sleep in the trees ,
so we don 't get bit by the snakes or spiders .
Felipe , our guide , claims we 're near the big river
where the Yacumos live in the village .
- Look at my feet . Fucking jungle !
- Alan , do you want some tea ?
[ Felipe yelling ]
[ Felipe speaking in foreign language ]
God , my leg !
[ group chattering ]
[ machete thudding ]
- [ Jack ] Kill it ! Kill it !
- Hold him down . - Grab his leg !
- Hold him down . Be quiet .
- You 're hurting me ! - Hold him down .
[ Felipe moans loudly ]
Hold him down !
[ Felipe moaning ]
- Felipe ! - Jesus !
- [ Felipe ] Cut my leg .
- [ Alan ] Oh , Christ !
Machete . - Cut it off !
Cut it off ! Put it on the fire !
- [ Alan ] Come on , do it !
Do it !
[ Felipe moaning ]
Come on ! Do it here !
- You 're still shooting ?
- [ Alan ] Yeah ! Do it now !
I 'm getting it all !
Do it ! Come on !
[ machete thuds ]
[ Felipe screams ] [ dramatic music ]
- [ Mark ] Come on , come on . Chop it !
[ dramatic music ]
[ flesh sizzling ]
[ flesh hissing ] [ dramatic music ]
- [ Alan ] Felipe was a great buddy and a top notch guide .
We 'll miss him .
But even more , we 'll miss the security he gave us .
We 've decided to go on ,
but now we 've only got the compass
and our instincts to show the way .
[ film reel clicking ]
- [ Jack ] Panning to you , Alan .
Okay , give us an earth shattering statement .
- You know this is gonna make us famous .
- [ Jack ] Yeah , you think so , huh ?
How famous ? - Yeah .
Real famous and real rich .
- [ Jack ] Yeah ?
- What are you gonna do with your money ?
- [ Jack ] I 'm gonna buy a house and a piece of ass .
[ Alan chuckles ]
Think that 's funny , huh ?
- Yeah , that 's the only way you can get it .
Where 's Faye ?
- [ Jack ] I don 't know .
- Turn the camera off , will ya ?
[ Jack whistles ]
Christ , what 's taking you so long ?
- Well , I had to wait in line with the rest of the animals .
[ Alan chuckles ]
You 're disgusting !
[ Jack laughs ] - Hey , get outta here .
I told you to get outta here with the camera !
- [ Jack ] I just wanna little peek .
- Will you get outta here ?
Get outta here with that thing .
Get outta here .
Come on , I told you to turn the goddamn thing off !
- [ Faye ] I 'll get you .
- Woo !
[ Faye grunts ]
[ bird squawking ]
- Come on , slaves ! Push .
Look , there 's a caiman .
Get outta the water !
- No-no , forget about me ! Film it .
Film it !
- [ Mark ] Come on , Alan , jump in the boat !
- [ Faye ] Come on , get on the raft , you guys !
- Get a shot of the alligator !
Hurry up !
[ Jack groans ]
Ah , a snake !
We 're saved by the anaconda .
Saved from the jaws of death .
Oh !
[ water splashing ]
Swim !
[ birds squawking ]
Come on .
[ Yacumos chattering ]
I wonder where their village is ?
Just shoot in the air and we 'll follow them .
- And when they scatter , how we gonna get there ?
[ monkey screeching ]
[ dramatic music ] [ monkey screams ]
[ tribe chattering ]
[ birds squawking ]
I got it . Give me the gun !
- [ Alan ] No , wait !
- [ Jack ] I know what I 'm doing .
[ gun fires ]
- [ Alan ] Why ? - [ Jack ] Don 't you get it ?
We could never keep up with them in the jungle .
[ Yacumo person moaning ]
This way that buck 'll go slow enough
to take us right to the village .
[ film reel clicking ]
- Well , what do you think , Professor ?
- That it 's not the best way of establishing peace
with the Yacumo tribe .
Now , I 'm beginning to understand
why they greeted us with such hostility .
- You think this is bad .
This is nothing .
Alan did much worse . Just watch .
[ film reel clicking ]
[ birds screeching ]
They could play it rough when they felt they had to .
Remember how they set up some of those executions .
[ wood cracks ]
[ film reel clicking ]
[ Yacumo chattering ]
[ wounded person moaning ]
- [ Mark ] Faye !
[ Yacumo chattering ]
[ pig squeals ]
[ gun fires ] [ pig screams ]
[ pig whimpers ]
- Here we are at the edge of the world in human history .
Things like this happen all the time in the jungle .
It 's survival of the fittest .
In-in the jungle , it 's the daily violence
of the strong overcoming of the weak !
Jack !
[ gun fires ]
[ Yacumo clamoring ]
[ gun firing ]
- [ Mark ] Yah , yah ! Come on let 's go !
[ gun fires ] Let 's go !
- [ Jack ] Yee ! yah , yah !
- [ Mark ] Come on , get up ! Come on , let 's go !
- [ Jack ] Go-go-go-go !
- [ Alan ] Jack !
- [ Mark ] Get the fuck in there you [ indistinct ] !
Come on , come on , come on come on , come on , come on !
Get up !
- [ Jack ] Get out of here !
[ Alan shouting ]
- [ Alan ] Jack , a torch !
[ Yacumos muttering ]
Ready ?
Okay , the massacre of the Yacumos by the Yamamomos ! Right !
- [ Harold ] A set up ! All a set up !
Just like Cambodia .
- [ Faye ] Get this fucker !
[ anxious music ]
- [ Mark ] Eh ?
- [ Alan ] That 's it ! That 's it !
[ Jack shouts ]
[ ominous music ]
Move it in ! Move it in !
[ dramatic music ]
[ fire crackling ] [ Yacumos moaning ]
- [ Alan ] Get them inside ! Get them inside !
[ dramatic music ]
- Get in ! Get in !
[ Yacumos screaming ] [ dramatic music ]
[ fire crackling ]
[ Yacumos screaming ]
- [ Alan ] Get them back inside !
[ troubling upbeat music ]
[ Yacumos screaming ]
It 's beautiful !
[ Yacumos screaming ] [ troubling upbeat music ]
- Alan , here !
- All right !
[ troubling upbeat music ]
[ fire crackling ]
[ birds chirping ]
[ both muttering faintly ]
Ow , ow !
[ Alan grunts ]
[ Faye panting ]
- [ Faye ] Do it , Alan .
[ Alan chuckles ]
- [ Alan ] Show them how we do it here .
[ Alan moans ]
[ both panting ]
[ Jack laughs ]
Oh , oh , you motherfucker !
Get the fuck outta here .
You believe this ?
You fucking turkey .
[ Alan chuckles ] [ film reel clicking ]
- Whew , I 'm drained .
You must admit it 's exceptional footage .
I didn 't expect such impact , such authenticity .
- I don 't know .
I don 't think exceptional 's the right word .
- You don 't ?
- No .
I mean what 's exceptional about a primitive tribe
like the Yacumo be terrorized
and forced into doing something they don 't ,
they don 't normally do .
- Come on now , Professor . Let 's be realistic .
Who knows anything about the Yacumo civilization ?
Today , people want sensationalism .
The more you rape their senses , the happier they are .
- Ah , yes , that 's typical Western thought .
Civilized isn 't it ?
That 's what Alan thought and that 's why he 's dead .
The Yacumo Indian is a primitive
and he has to be respected as such .
You know did you ever think of the Yacumo point of view
that we might be the ones who are savages ?
- Well , I never thought of it that way ,
but it 's an interesting idea .
- Yes . Let 's say things were reversed , right .
And the Yacumo attacked your house ,
defiled everything that you held holy .
You know that pig that was killed ,
that was food for those people .
Now , what 'd happen if somebody came into your house
when you were hungry
and-and took the little bit of food
you had in the refrigerator and threw it down the toilet ?
Would you behave in a civilized way ?
Would you like people to make money off your misery ?
- We have succeeded in establishing ,
shall we say , diplomatic relations with the Yacumos ,
but what are we for them ?
These are people who have never seen a White man before
or heard the sound of a gun .
We know they are really afraid of our powers ,
but for how long
and can we really be sure that they don 't hate us ?
Like most people hate what they don 't -
[ Yacumo gasping ]
When the old members of the tribe feel death approaching ,
they wander off to a secluded spot .
After she dies , this old woman .
- This old woman will probably end up as lunch
for some alligator .
In the jungle , nothing goes to waste .
Nature recycles everything .
[ Yacumos chanting ]
You 're about to witness an ancient ritual
never before seen by civilized man .
The tribe is a primitive social unit
bound together by the basic needs of survival .
[ Yacumos chanting ]
To protect itself ,
the tribe must eliminate any diseased elements .
Now don 't go away .
What you 're about to see
may simply be described as social surgery .
[ Yacumos chanting ]
[ dramatic music ]
[ group wailing ]
[ Yacumos chattering ]
[ rock thudding ]
[ person yelps ]
[ dramatic music ]
We had a long discussion last night
about whether to keep going or turn back .
Wasn 't easy to come to an agreement .
Perhaps , the others are right .
Maybe we shouldn 't push our luck .
God knows we 've been lucky so far .
But you know what finally convinced them ?
The chance to become famous .
To reach that spot where time stopped
three or 4,000 years ago .
Where the Yamamomos ,
the Tree People , live , ugh , in constant strife
with their , their enemies the Shamataris .
See this guy ?
This was a Yamamomo warrior killed by the Yacumos .
Just to give you an idea ,
to the Yacumos this is a savage .
[ film reel clicking ]
- I 'm not speaking as a scientist ,
but as the man on the street .
This so-called documentary footage is offensive ,
it is dishonest and , above all , it is inhuman .
- Yes-yes , of course .
We all know what Alan was like .
He over did it as usual .
But what you saw is a rough cut .
- Perhaps I haven 't made myself clear .
But I , I refuse to have anything to do with this material .
- Look , Professor , we are talking about
the most sensational documentary to come along in years .
But , and you want us just to shelve it ?
To forget about , as if it had never been found ?
Is that what you want ?
- Yes , yes . That is precisely what I want .
I 've seen the rest of the material , you haven 't .
You haven 't seen the stuff that even your editors
didn 't have the stomach to put together
and if you had , you wouldn 't hesitate but to agree with me .
[ door clicks ]
- John , go ahead .
[ film reel clicking ]
[ birds squawking ]
[ metal clacking ]
- We 're somewhere in the middle of this Green Inferno
where no civilized man has ever been before .
- [ Mark ] Look at that .
- Huh . The jungle here 's different .
It 's almost hospitable ,
but so far we 've seen no sign yet of the Tree People ,
the Yamamomos .
- Good ?
Like ? - We 're beginning to wonder
if they really exist or if they 're just a legend .
[ grass rustling ]
- [ Mark ] Alan !
- [ Alan ] I think we got one !
Grab her ! You got her ?
- I got her , yeah .
- Look what we found .
- Here is the little monkey and look .
- Some taste you guys have , she stinks .
She 's marked .
What do you think she is a Yamamomo or a Shamatari ?
- How should I know . Why don 't you ask her ?
- What do you wanna do with her ?
- I 'll take care of the little monkey .
- Judging from the looks of this girl ,
we finally found the Yamamomos , the Tree People
But we 're gonna have to be very careful ,
because these people are known for their cruelty .
- Get her ! Come on .
- Alright . Alright .
Ah , I got this little monkey .
Ah , you go first .
[ Alan laughs ]
- Okay , oh , drop on her .
Yeah , all right .
[ Alan chuckles ]
Whew !
- [ Mark ] Okay , hold her tight !
- Ah , go ahead . All right .
All right .
- Sorry . Open .
[ Alan moans ]
- Jack , what do you wanna use it for ?
A porno film ? Stupid ass !
- That 's not a bad idea . How about Jungle Jollies ?
[ Alan laughs ]
- [ Jack ] Hey , you want me to keep shooting ?
You want me to keep shooting or what ?
- That 's a stupid question .
Hurry up , Casanova . It 's Jack 's turn .
- [ Mark ] Come on !
- Jack 's next .
Okay , Jack , go ahead .
- [ Mark ] Come on .
That 's all right .
Oh , look at the little kid
[ Faye ] We have only three cans of film !
We can 't use this !
Why do you wanna waste it like that ?
- [ Alan ] Shut up !
- Hey , aren 't you gonna get some , Alan ?
- [ Faye ] The only thing he gets off on is his camera !
- [ Jack ] Whew-hoo .
- [ Alan ] Okay , Mark .
- [ Jack ] Come on in here !
- [ Faye ] Stop shooting , Mark .
[ Alan moans ]
[ blows smacking ]
Stop it , Alan !
[ Alan moans ]
[ blow thuds ] You bastard !
- [ Alan ] Get her , Jack . Get her off [ indistinct ] !
[ Faye groans ]
[ hand smacking ]
[ Alan groans ]
[ hand slapping ]
- [ Faye ] God damn you !
- He 's changing reels .
[ gentle music ]
[ foliage rustling ]
- [ Alan ] All right , move in tight . Tight .
Oh , come in for a close up .
[ sombre music ]
- [ Mark ] Watch it , Alan , I 'm shooting .
- Oh , good Lord !
It 's [ exhales ] , it 's unbelievable .
It 's , it 's horrible .
I can 't understand the reason for such cruelty .
It must have something to do with some obscure sexual rite
or with the almost profound respect
these primitives have for virginity .
[ sombre music ]
[ film reel clicking ]
[ birds warbling ]
You 're rolling , Mark ?
- [ Mark ] Yeah .
[ foliage rustling ] [ birds chirping ]
Look up there on the right !
- [ Mark ] Christ , they 're all around us .
[ gun fires ]
[ film reel clicking ] [ birds warbling ]
- [ Alan ] Keep rolling !
We 're gonna get an Oscar for this !
[ gun fires ]
[ tribe members shouting ]
[ foliage rustling ]
[ spear bangs ]
[ gun fires ]
Jack ! - Jack !
- Jack ! - Jack !
- [ Faye ] Alan , you can 't !
You can 't ! - Look , he 's had it anyway !
- No , he 's still alive , you bastard !
You can 't !
- What about you , Mark ?
- [ Mark ] Yes ! - Get the fuck off me !
- [ Faye ] You can 't !
- [ Alan ] God damn it !
[ gun fires ]
[ Faye wails ]
[ dramatic music ]
[ tribe chattering ]
Keep filming , Mark . I 'll cover you .
- [ Mark ] You got it ! Right down to the last foot .
[ dramatic music ] [ tribe chattering ]
[ gun fires ]
[ dramatic music ]
[ tribe shouting ]
[ gun fires ]
[ dramatic music ]
[ tribe chattering ]
[ blows thudding ]
[ dramatic music ]
[ dramatic music ] [ tribe chattering ]
[ sombre music ]
[ rhythmic troubling music ]
[ intense music ] [ tribe chattering ]
[ dramatic music ]
[ intense dramatic music ]
[ film reel clicking ] [ birds chirping ]
- We really screwed ourselves this time .
Trying to , trying to stay there for the last shot .
I don 't even know where we are now .
But I know they , I know they , uh , they followed us
and , and we lost everything trying to escape .
We 're screwed ! We 're trapped !
Gonna try to scare away with this .
I hope it works
[ flare gun fires ]
[ explosion crackles ]
Stay by me , Faye .
- [ Faye ] Alan ! - [ Alan ] Don 't get far away !
Stay over here !
You motherfuckers !
- [ Faye ] Alan !
[ flare gun fires ]
[ explosion crackles ]
Help me !
- Faye !
Faye ! [ Faye screams ]
Hey , stop ! - They got her !
- [ Alan ] Stop ! Stop !
- [ Mark ] Leave her be , Alan .
She 's had it !
Hey , we gotta think of ourselves .
[ Alan hysterically muttering ]
We got to get the film back home , Alan !
Think of the film . [ blow thudding ]
Think of the film !
[ tribe shouting ]
[ dramatic music ]
[ Faye screams ]
[ dramatic music ] [ Faye screams ]
[ tribe chanting ]
- Stop ! No !
[ Faye moans ]
[ intense dramatic music ]
[ Faye screams ] [ tribe chanting ]
No !
[ Faye moans ]
[ frenzied music ]
[ tribe whooping ]
[ Faye screaming ]
[ troubling upbeat music ]
[ intense dramatic music ]
[ tribe chanting ]
[ dramatic music ]
[ intense dramatic music ]
- [ Executive ] John , I want this material burned .
All of it . Yeah .
[ receiver clicks ]
[ traffic noise humming ]
- [ Harold ] I wonder who the real cannibals are ?
[ gentle upbeat music ]